Chapter 18. The return journey.
When Bilbo came to himself, he was literally by himself. He was lying on
the flat stones of Ravenhill, and no one was near. A cloudless day, but cold, was
broad above him. He was shaking and as chilled as stone, but his head burned
with fire. "Now I wonder what has happened," he said to himself. "At any
rate, I am not yet one of the fallen heroes, but I suppose there is still
time enough for that." He sat up painfully, looking into the valley, he
could see no living goblins. After a while, as his head cleared a little, he
thought he could see elves moving in the rocks below. He rubbed his eyes. Surely
there was a camp still in the plane some distance off, and there was a coming and
going about the gate. Dwarves seemed to be busy removing the wall, but all was
deadly still. There was no call and no echo of a song. Sorrow seemed to be in
the air. "Victory after all, I suppose," he said, feeling his aching head. "Well,
it seems a very gloomy business.
Suddenly he was aware of a man climbing up and coming towards him. "Hello
there," he called with a shaky voice.
"Hello there! What news?" "What voice is it that speaks among the stones?" said
the man, halting and peering about him, not far from where Bilbo sat. "Then
Bilbo remembered his ring." "Well, I'm blessed," said he. "This invisibility
has its drawbacks after all. Otherwise, I suppose I might have spent a warm and
comfortable night in bed. "It's me, Bilbo Baggins, companion of Thoren," he
cried hurriedly, taking off the ring.
"It is well that I have found you," said the man, striding forward. "You are
needed, and we have looked for you long.
You would have been numbered among the dead, who are many, if Gandalf the
wizard had not said that your voice was last heard in this place. I have been
sent to look here for the last time. Are you much hurt? A nasty knock on the
head, I think, said Bilbo. But I have a helm and a hard skull. All the same, I
feel sick, and my legs are like straws.
I will carry you down to the camp in the valley, said the man, and picked him
lightly up. The man was swift and shorefooted. It was not long before
Bilbo was set down before a tent in Dale, and there stood Gandalf with his
arm in a sling. Even the wizard had not escaped without a wound, and there were
few unharmed in all the host. When Gandalf saw Bilbo, he was delighted.
Baggins, he exclaimed, "Well, I never alive after all. I am glad. I began to
wonder if even your luck would see you through." A terrible business, and it
nearly was disastrous. But other news can wait. "Come," he said more gravely.
You are called for and leading the hobbit he took him within the tent. Hail
Thoren, he said as he entered, I have brought him. There indeed lay Thoren
Oaken shield, wounded with many wounds, and his rent armor and notched ax were
cast upon the floor. He looked up as Bilbo came beside him. Farewell, good
thief, he said. I go now to the halls of waiting to sit beside my fathers until
the world is renewed. Since I leave now all gold and silver, and go where it is
of little worth, I wish to pardon friendship from you, and I would take
back my words and deeds at the gate."
Bilbo knelt on one knee filled with sorrow. "Farewell, king under the
mountain," he said. "This is a bitter adventure if it must end so, and not a
mountain of gold can amend it. Yet I am glad that I have shared in your perils
that has been more than any Baggins deserves.
No, said Thorin, there is more in you of good than you know, child of the kindly
West, some courage and some wisdom blended in measure. If more of us valued
food and cheer and song above hoarded gold, it would be a merrier world. But
sad or merry, I must leave it now.
Farewell.
Then Bilbo turned away and he went by himself and sat alone wrapped in a
blanket. And whether you believe it or not, he wept until his eyes were red and
his voice was horsearo. He was a kindly little soul. Indeed, it was long before
he had the heart to make a joke again.
A mercy it is, he said at last to
himself, that I woke up when I did. I am glad that we parted in kindness. You are
a fool, Bilbo Baggins, and you made a great mess of that business with the
stone, and there was a battle in spite of all your efforts to buy peace and
quiet. But I suppose you can hardly be blamed for that. All that had happened
after he was stunned, Bilbo learned later, but it gave him more sorrow than
joy, and he was now weary of his adventure. He was aching in his bones
for the homeward journey. That, however, was a little delayed, so in the
meantime, I will tell something of events. The eagles had long had
suspicion of the goblin's mustering.
From their watchfulness the movements in the mountains could not be altogether
hid, so they too had gathered in great numbers under the great eagle of the
Misty Mountains, and at length, smelling battle from afar, they had come speeding
down the gale in the nick of time. They was who dislodged the goblins from the
mountain slopes, casting them over precipaces, or driving them down,
shrieking and bewildered among their foes. It was not long before they had
freed the lonely mountain, and elves and men on either side of the valley could
come at last to the help of the battle below. But even with the eagles, they
were still outnumbered. In that last hour himself had appeared. No one knew
how or from where. He came alone and in bear shape, and he seemed to have grown
almost to giant size in his wrath. The roar of his voice was like drums and
guns, and he tossed wolves and goblins from his path like straws and feathers.
He fell upon their rear and broke like a clap of thunder through the ring. The
dwarves were making a stand still about their lords upon a low rounded hill.
Then Bejorn stooped and lifted Thoren, who had fallen pierced with spears, and
bore him out of the fray. Swiftly he returned, and his wrath was redoubled,
so that nothing could withstand him, and no weapon seemed to bite upon him. He
scattered the bodyguard, and pulled down Bold himself, and crushed him. Then
dismay fell on the goblins, and they fled in all directions. But weariness
left their enemies with the coming of new hope, and they pursued them closely,
and prevented most of them from escaping where they could. They drove many of
them into the running river, and such as fled south or west they hunted into the
marshes about the forest river, and there the greater part of the last
fugitives perished, while those that came hardly to the wood elves realm were
there slain or drawn in to die deep in the trackless dark of Murkwood. Songs
have said that three parts of the goblin warriors of the north perished on that
day, and the mountains had peace for many a year. Victory had been assured
before the fall of night, but the pursuit was still on foot when Bilbo
returned to the camp, and not many were in the valley saved the more grievously
wounded. "Where are the eagles?" he asked Gandalf that evening, as he lay
wrapped in many warm blankets. "Some are in the hunt," said the wizard, "but most
have gone back to their IE. They would not stay here, and departed with the
first light of morning. Dne has crowned their chief with gold and sworn
friendship with them forever.
I am sorry. I mean, I should have liked to see them again, said Bilbo sleepily.
Perhaps I shall see them on the way home. I suppose I shall be going home
soon. As soon as you like, said the wizard. Actually, it was some days
before Bilbo really set out. They buried Doran deep beneath the mountain and Bard
laid the arkan stone upon his breast.
There let a lie to the mountain falls.
He said, "May it bring good fortune to all his folk that dwell here after upon
his tomb the elven king then laid orchrist the elvish sword that had been
taken from Thorin in captivity. It is said in songs that it gleamed ever in
the dark if foes approached, and the fortress of the dwarves could not be
taken by surprise. There now Dne, son of Naine, took up his abode, and he became
king under the mountain, and in time many other dwarves gathered to his
throne in the ancient halls. Of the 12 companions of Thoren, 10 remained.
Feelely and Keely had fallen, defending him with shield and body, for he was
their mother's elder brother. The others remained with Dne,
for Dne dealt his treasure well. There was of course no longer any question of
dividing the horde in such shares as had been planned to Balin and Dwellan and
Dori and Dori and Aie and Owen and Gloin and by Fur and Bulfor and Bombore to
Bilbo. Yet a 14th share of all the silver and gold rot and unrot was given
up to Bard. For Dne said, "We will honor the agreement of the dead, and he has
now the Arkan stone in his keeping."
Even a 14th share was wealth exceedingly great, greater than that of many mortal
kings. From that treasure, B sent much gold to the master of Lake Town, and he
rewarded his followers and friends freely. To the elven king he gave the
emeralds of Jiren, such jewels as he most loved, which Dne had restored to
him. To Bilbo, he said, "This treasure is as much yours as it is mine. Though
old agreements cannot stand, since so many have a claim in its winning and
defense, yet even though you are willing to lay aside all your claim, I should
wish that the words of Thorin, of which he repented, should not prove true that
we should give you little. I would reward you most richly of all." Very
kind of you, said Bilbo. But really, it is a relief to me. How on earth should I
have got all that treasure home without war and murder all along the way? I
don't know, and I don't know what I should have done with it when I got
home. I am sure it is better in your hands. In the end, he would only take
two small chests, one filled with silver and the other with gold, such as one
strong pony could carry. That will be quite as much as I can manage, said he.
At last the time came for him to say goodbye to his friends.
Farewell Balon, he said. And farewell, Dwellan, and farewell, Dory, Nori, Oi,
Oin, Gloin, Bloin by Fur.
Bofer, Bofur, and Bomb.
May your beards never grow thin.
And turning towards the mountain, he added, "Farewell Thor and Oaken Shield
and Fely and Tilly."
May your men of B. Then the dwarves bowed low before their gate, but words
stuck in their throats. "Goodbye and good luck, wherever you fare," said
Balin at last. If ever you visit us again, when our halls are made fair once
more, then the feast shall indeed be splendid.
If ever you are passing my way, said Bilbo. Don't wait to knock. Tea is it
for, but any of you are welcome at any time. Then he turned away. The elf host
was on the march, and if it was sadly lessened, yet many were glad, for now
the northern world would be marrier for many a long day. The dragon was dead,
and the goblins overthrown, and their hearts looked forward after winter to a
spring of joy. Gandalf and Bilbo rode behind the elven king, and beside them
strode Bejorn, once again in man's shape, and he laughed and sang in a loud
voice upon the road. So they went on until they drew near to the borders of
Murkwood, to the north of the place where the forest river ran out. Then
they halted, for the wizard and Bilbo would not enter the wood, even though
the king bade them stay a while in his halls. They intended to go along the
edge of the forest and round its northern end in the waste that lay
between it and the beginning of the gray mountains. It was a long and cheerless
road, but now that the goblins were crushed, it seemed safer to them than
the dreadful pathways under the trees.
The oasil beern was going that way, too.
Farewell, oh Elvin King, said Gandalf. Mary be the Greenwood, while the world is yet young,
and merry be all your folk. Farewell, oh Gandalf, said the king, may you ever
appear where you are most needed and least expected. The often you appear in
my halls, the better shall I be pleased.
I beg of you, said Bilbo, stammering and standing on one foot, to accept this
gift. And he brought out a necklace of silver and pearls that Dne had given him
at their parting. In what way have I earned such a gift, oh hobbit, said the
king? Well, Eru, I thought, don't you know, said Bilbo, rather confused, that
he some little return should be made for your hospitality. I mean, even a burglar
has his feelings. I have drunk much of your wine and eaten much of your bread.
I will take your gift, oh Bilbo the Magnificent, said the king gravely, and
I name you elf friend and blessed. May your shadow never grow less, or stealing
would be too easy. Farewell.
Then the elves turned towards the forest, and Bilbo started on his long
road home. He had many hardships and adventures before he got back. The wild
was still the wild, and there were many other things in it in those days beside
goblins, but he was well-guided and well-guarded. The wizard was with him,
and bejorn for much of the way, and he was never in great danger again. Anyway,
by mid-inter Gandalf and Bilbo had come all the way back along both edges of the
forest to the doors of Bejorn's house, and there for a while they both stayed.
Ule tide was warm and merry there, and men came from far and wide to feast at
Bejorn's bidding. The goblins of the Misty Mountains were now few and
terrified, and hidden in the deepest holes they could find, and the wars had
vanished from the woods, so that men went abroad without fear. Beern indeed
became a great chief afterwards in those regions, and ruled a wide land between
the mountains and the wood. And it is said that for many generations the men
of his line had the power of taking bear's shape, and some were grim men and
bad, but most were in heart like Bejorn, if less in size and strength. In their
day, the last goblins were hunted from the Misty Mountains, and a new peace
came over the edge of the wild. It was spring and a fair one with mild weathers
and a bright sun before Bilbo and Gandalf took their leave at last of
Bejorn. And though he longed for home, Bilbo left with regret, for the flowers
of the gardens of Bejorn were in springtime no less marvelous than in
high summer. At last they came up the long road and reached the very pass
where the goblins had captured them before.
But they came to that high point at morning, and looking backward they saw a
white sun shining over the outstretched lands. There behind lay Murkwood, blue
in the distance, and darkly green at the nearer edge, even in the spring. There,
far away was the lonely mountain on the edge of eyesight. On its highest peak,
snow yet unmelted, was gleaming pale. So come snow after fire, and even dragons
have their ending, said Bilbo, and he turned his back on his adventure. The
Turkish part was getting very tired, and the Baggins was daily getting stronger.
I wish now only to be in my own armchair, he said. Chapter 19, the last